Finding Aid for the Carleton Watkins Collection of Photographs LSC.0599
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carleton Watkins collection of photographs
circa 1867-1882
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0599
6 oversize boxes
The collection consists of 136 photographs, with the majority being from Watkins's California mission series, Yosemite series, and pacific coast series. A few additional prints are from the Columbia River and Oregon series, studio portraits, and various images from the Southwest, such as Casa Grande, San Marino, New Almaden Mines, and Pasadena. Carleton E. Watkins was born in Oneonta, Oswego County, New York, on November 11, 1829. Watkins moved to California in 1854, where he eventually established his own photographic studio, then spent large portions of the summer traveling with his cameras throughout California. In 1861, Watkins visited the Yosemite Valley and made the first 18" x 22" landscape photographs in California. He also is also believed to have created the earliest photographs of the California Missions. Watkins died on June 23, 1916.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Online Items Availabe note for the link to the digitized materials.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carl Dentzel, 1954
Gift of Anita and Gregory Carter, 1955
Gift of Martin R. Huberty, n.d.
UCLA Special Collections purchase, 1973.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9975427793606533
Biography
Carleton E. Watkins was born in Oneonta, Oswego County, New York, on November 11, 1829. He was the youngest of five children of a Scottish innkeeper. During his youth he became acquainted with Collis P. Huntington, who frequented his father's hotel. Soon after the discovery of gold, both young men went to California, where Huntington later became one of the Big Four who built the Central Pacific Railroad.
In 1854, while working as a clerk in a store on Montgomery Street, Watkins met R. H. Vance, the daguerreotyper who had studios in San Francisco, San Jose and Sacramento. The employee at Vance's San Jose studio had suddenly quit and Vance asked Watkins if he would fill in until a permanent replacement could be found. Although he knew nothing of photographic processes, Watkins agreed. For the first few days he was simply the care-taker of the studio, but when Vance could not find a new operator, he instructed Watkins in coating the daguerreotype plates and making exposures. With only the briefest instructions, Watkins was able to make portraits and completely operated the gallery for a short period. In 1857 or 1858 Watkins returned to San Francisco where he established his own photographic studio for portraits and view photography. Watkins usually spent a large portion of the summer traveling throughout California, leaving his gallery and studio in the hands of an assistant. In 1858 or 1859 he visited the Mariposa Grove and was the first person to photograph the "Grizzly Giant." In 1861, Watkins visited the Yosemite Valley and made the first 18" x 22" landscape photographs in California (and possibly the world). He made many more trips to Yosemite during the 1860s and 1870s.
In 1868 Watkins made his first trip to Oregon, where he made the first photographic reproductions of the Columbia River. Five years later, Watkins went to Utah with his wagon, team and photographic equipment on railroad cars. Thanks to his friend Collis P. Huntington, he traveled free. He was accompanied on this trip by close friend and artist William Keith, who made extensive use of Watkins photographs for many of his oil paintings.
During the winter of 1871-72, Watkins expanded his San Francisco gallery (the Yosemite Gallery), which put an extra strain on his finances. When the Bank of California went under in 1874, Watkins lost his Yosemite Art Galley to competitors J.J. Cook and I.W. Taber. Not only did his competitors take over his Gallery, they took all of his negatives as well. Watkins then began the task of rebuilding his collection, which meant rephotographing many of the sites he had visited earlier in his career. "Watkins's New Series" of views replaced those lost in the foreclosure. Watkins did become reassociated with the Yosemite Gallery, first as a photographer, and later as manager, but never as the owner.
Watkins went to the Comstock Lode, near Virginia City, Nevada, in 1876. It was probably during this trip that he met Frances Sneed, who later managed his Montgomery Street studio and became his wife on November 11, 1880 (Watkins's fiftieth birthday). They had two children: a daughter, Julia and a son, Collis.
In 1880, Watkins went to Southern California for the first time and traveled along the line of the Southern Pacific Railroad. Later he went to the "End of the Track" and as far as Tombstone, Arizona. The photographs taken by Watkins on this trip represent some of the earliest views of San Bernardino, San Gabriel, Pasadena, Los Angeles and San Diego. On the way back to San Francisco, he followed the old overland stage road, traveling the greater part of the way in his wagon and photographing most of the Franciscan missions. These pictures constitute the earliest photographic collection of California Missions. On a second trip to the Northwest in 1890, Watkins made a series of stereoscopic views in Victoria, B. C. He extended this trip into Montana where he made 18" x 22" views of the Anaconda copper mines and other properties. His last large commercial job and long country trip was to photograph the development work of the Kern County Land Company near Bakersfield. He made seven hundred views using 8" x 10" dry plate negatives. In the late 1890s, Watkins began to photograph the Hearst Hacienda near Pleasanton for Phoebe Apperson Hearst, but ill health prevented him from completing the assignment.
Watkins was in the process of negotiating with Stanford University for the sale of his plates, photographs, etc. when the 1906 earthquake struck San Francisco. By this time, Watkins was partially blind, in poor health and experiencing financial difficulties. He had been living with his family in his studio on the top floor of a building on the southeast corner of Ninth and Market Streets. Immediately following the quake, Watkins's wife and daughter went to the refugee camp at the Presidio. Watkins was led by his son to the home of his old friend, C. B. Turrill, who had assisted Watkins financially in the past. Watkins's entire collection was destroyed in the fire which followed the quake. He was shocked by the loss of his life's work and shortly thereafter retired to his small ranch near Capay in Yolo County. The ranch had been deeded to Watkins through the offices of Collis P. Huntington of the Southern Pacific Railroad for his faithful, but unpaid, service to the railroad.
Watkins never recovered from the shock of losing his entire collection in the San Francisco fire. He managed to live at the ranch with his family until it became necessary to have him committed to the Napa State Hospital at Imola, California in 1910. He died on June 23, 1916 at the age of eighty-seven and was buried on the hospital grounds.
(from: The Early Pacific Coast Photographs of Carleton E.Watkins, by J. W. Johnson, Professor of Hydraulic Engineering, University of California Berkeley, and The Life and Photography of Carleton E.Watkins, by Peter E. Palmquist.)
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 136 photographs: 85 albumen mammoth prints, 52 assorted smaller prints (primarily cabinet and boudoir cards), and 5 non-original copies of Watkins photographs. The majority of the photographs are from Watkins's California mission series, Yosemite series, and pacific coast series. Watkins is believed to be the earliest known photographer to create images of the California missions, and the collection includes most of the missions found in the state. A few additional prints are from the Columbia River and Oregon series, studio portraits, and various images from the Southwest, such as Casa Grande, San Marino, New Almaden Mines, and Pasadena.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Carleton Watkins Collection of Photographs (36 items).
Related Items Available Online
Related material to this collection has been digitized and is available online: Yosemite photographs by Carleton E. Watkins (F868.Y6 P5 1867).
Pacific States -- Photographs.; Yosemite National Park (Calif.) -- Photographs.; Spanish mission buildings -- California -- Photographs.
- Columbia River and Oregon
  - [The Middle Landing from the Oregon Side], [1867]; ID no. SCW1; Plate Dimensions: 40x51.5 Matt Dimensions: 55.5x71 Mammoth print Foxing in TL. All edges cockled. All corners creased. Foxing all along BE. Black smudges on BE 12" from RE. Foxing on TC. Spot 6" from TE & 1" from LE. (Box 2)
  - [O.N.S. side-wheel steamer, Oneonta meeting the transcontinental train at the Colombia river, Oregon territory], [1867?]; Watkins Series no. 438; Plate Dimensions: 39.5x52.5 Matt Dimensions: 48.5x61.5 Mammoth print Stains: 7-1/4" from LE & 5-1/5" from TE; 5-1/2" from LE & 3-1/4 from TE; 7-1/4" from LE & 1-1/2" from TE. LE surface losses 4", 4-1/2", 5-5/8" from BE. BRC creased and surface loss. BRC series of water marks. Stain 6-1/2" from TE, 1-1/4" from RE. Water stains on TRC; 1-1/2" from TE & 5-3/4" from LE; 3-3/4" from LE & 3/4" from TE; 4" from TE & 1/4" from LE, 9" from BE & 1" from LE. Water stains on BE: 2-1/2", 4-1/2", 6-3/4", 9-1/2", 17", 22" from LE. TE abrasion 9-1/2" from RE. (Box 2)
  - [O.N.S. side-wheel steamer, Oneonta meeting the transcontinental train at the Colombia river, Oregon territory], [1867?]; Watkins Series no. 438; Plate Dimensions: 10.5x15 Copy (not original) (Box 1, Folder 2/5)
- Missions
  - Mission San Gabriel, Copy (not original) (Box Missing)
  - Mission Santa Barbara, Established Dec. 4th, 1786. Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco, Watkins Series no. 4646; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - [Mission Santa Inez, Estab. Sept. 17th, 1804.] Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco, Watkins Series no. 4652; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - Mission Santa Inez, Established Sept. 17th, 1804. Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco., Watkins Series no. 4653; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - Mission San Miguel, Established July 25th, 1797. Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco., Watkins Series no. 4656; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - [San Carlos del Carmelo Mission], ID no. SCW14; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - [San Carlos del Carmelo Mission] Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco, ID no. SCW15; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - [San Carlos del Carmelo Mission (Interior)] Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco, ID no. SCW16; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - [Mission San Carlos del Carmelo (Interior)] Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco, ID no. SCW17; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - Mission, San Diego San Diego County, California, Established July 16th, 1769., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1201; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print Black spot, 6" from TE and 5" from LE. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC, BRC, TRC loss. BE discolored. RE very discolored. Surface loss at 7", 9-3/4", 14-3/4", 18-1/4" from LE. RE: 1-1/2" tear, 3-1/4" from BE. TE: surface loss, 12-1/2" from RE. Surface loss TLC. (Box 2)
  - Mission, San Diego San Diego County, California, Established July 16, 1769. From the Rear, looking down the Valley., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1202; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print Black spot, 6-1/2" from TE, 3-3/4" from RE. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. LE: cut, 5-1/4" from BE. BE: crease running 5" from LE parallel to BE. BE: surface loss, 1-1/2" from LE. BE: small tear, 7-3/8" from LE. BE: surface losses, 12-1/2: & 14-3/4" from LE. RE: grubby. RE: surface losses at 8", 11-1/4", 16-1/2" from BE. TRC missing. TE: small tear, 4-3/4" from RE. TLC: creased and surface loss. (Box 2)
  - Mission, San Diego San Diego County, California, Established July 16th, 1769. From the East Side., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1203; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print Small black mark, 5-1/4" from TE, 11-1/2" from LE. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC crease and loss. TRC & BRC loss. BE: surface loss, 3" from RE. TE: surface loss, 9-1/4" from RE. (Box 3)
  - Olive and Palm Orchard San Diego Mission., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1204; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. ELC creased and loss. BE: small tear and surface loss, 12-3/4" from LE. BE: small tear, 6-1/4" from RE. RE: small tear, 8-1/2" from BE. RE: surface loss, 3" from TE. (Box 3)
  - Mission, San Luis Rey de Francia San Diego County, California, Established June 13th, 1798., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1205; Plate Dimensions: 36 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC: loss. BE: surface loss, 7-1/2" from LE. BRC missing. RE: surface loss, 1-1/4" from BE. TRC missing. TLC: creased & loss. (Box 3)
  - Mission, San Louis Rey de Francia San Diego County, California. Established June 13th, 1798. From the North., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1207; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. All corners: loss. BE: discolored. 2 spots in TL. (Box 3)
  - Mission, San Luis Rey de Francia San Diego County, California. Established June 13th, 1798., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1208; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BE: small tear, 8-1/4" from LE. BE: surface loss, 12-1/4" from LE. BE: surface loss, 1-1/4" from RE. TE: dent & crease, 2-1/4" from RE. (Box 3)
  - Mission, San Juan Capistrano Los Angeles County, California. Established Nov. 1st, 1776., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1209; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. LE: 4" piece partially torn out from 6" to 2" from BE. Document repair tape on LE, 6" from BE. Loss on all corners. BE: surface loss, 10-1/4" from LE. TE: surface loss, 4" from RE. Spot in TC. (Box 3)
  - Mission, San Juan Capistrano Los Angeles County, California. Established November 1st, 1776., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1210; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC & BRC: loss & surface loss. RE: surface loss, 1-1/2" from BE. RE: small tear, 2-1/4" from BE. (Box 4)
  - Mission, San Juan Capistrano Los Angeles County, California. Established November 1st, 1776., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1211; Plate Dimensions: 37 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print Black spot, 9-3/8" from RE, 5-3/4" from TE. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC loss. BE: loss, 1" from LE. BE: surface loss, 1-3/4" from LE. BE: surface loss, 4-3/4" from LE. BE: creases and tear, 7" from LE. TRC loss. TE: 1/2" x 18" loss, 4 " from RE. TE: surface loss, 5-1/2" to 6-1/2" from RE. TLC: whole creased 1-1/2" from corner. (Box 4)
  - Mission, San Gabriel Los Angeles County, California. Established September 8th, 1771., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1212; Plate Dimensions: 37 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. Loss all 4 corners. BE: loss, 7-1/4" from RE. RE: tear, 5" from BE. RE: surface loss, 6-1/4" from TE. TE: surface loss, 14-1/2" from RE. (Box 4)
  - Mission, San Gabriel Los Angeles County, California. Established September 8th, 1771. From Residence of Mr. Howard, with Date Palm., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1213; Plate Dimensions: 37 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC, BRC, TRC loss. BE: small tear, 2- 1/4" from LE. BE: small tear, 2" from RE. RE: surface loss, 8-3/4" from BE. Spot in TC. (Box 4)
  - Mission [San Luis Rey] Watkins' New Cabinet Series. Yosemite and Pacific Coast, 427 Montgomery St., San Francisco, Watkins Series no. 4606; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - San Fernando Rey Los Angeles County, California, Established Sept. 8th, 1797., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1214; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC, TRC loss. BE: surface loss, 1/2" from RE. RE: small tear & crease, 7-5/8" from BE. TE: loss and surface loss, 1" from LE. (Box 4)
  - Mission, San Fernando Rey Los Angeles County, California, Established Sept. 8th, 1797., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1215; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC & TRC loss. BRC: corner & edge missing. (Box 9)
  - San Fernando Rey Los Angeles County, California, Established Sept. 8th, 1797. General View from the East., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1216; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print Spot 12" from LE, 8-1/4" from TE. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BLC, BRC: loss. BE: surface loss, 1-3/4" from LE. BE: small tear, 13-1/2" from LE. Surface losses: 6-1/2", 4" from RE. RE: surface loss, 1" from BE. TE: surface losses, 1-1/2", 9-1/2" to 10-1/4", 12", 13-1/2", 17", 22-3/4", 23-3/4", 24-3/4" from RE. (Box 5)
  - Mission, San Buenaventura Ventura County, California, Established March 31st, 1782., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1217; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. TLC, BLC, BRC loss. TRC: corner missing. RE: 2" tear, 1" from BE. BE: crease running up to tear 2" from RE. RE: surface loss, 5-1/2" from BE. (Box 5)
  - Mission, San Buenaventura Ventura County, California, Established March 31st, 1782. View from the West., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1218; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. All corners loss. Surface losses: 8-3/4", 12- 1/2", 16-3/4" from LE. BE: small tear, 12-1/2" from LE. RE: small tear, 1-3/4" from BE. (Box 5)
  - Mission, San Buenaventura Los Angeles County, California. Established March 31st, 1782. General View from the Rear., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1219; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print Mark 6-1/2" from TE, 3-3/4" from RE. Mark 7" from TE, 3-1/4" from RE. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. Loss all corners. Surface losses, 6-1/4", 9", 10", 24-1/4" from LE. RE: surface loss, 5-1/4" from BE. TE: surface loss, 1-1/4" from LE. (Box 5)
  - Mission, Santa Barbara Santa Barbara County, California, Established December 4, 1786., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1220; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue LE. BLC: 1/2" missing. RE: 1/2" tear, 2-1/4" from BE. Loss TRC & BRC. TE: small tear, 11-7/8" & 12-1/2" from RE. TE: small chip, 13-3/4" from RE. TE: surface losses, 7-8" from LE. (Box 6)
  - Mission, Santa Barbara Santa Barbara County, California, Established December 4, 1786., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1221; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue LE. Loss BRC and TRC. BE: 1/2" tear, 5-1'2" from LE. BE: small chip, 8-1/2" from RE. TE: loss, 10" from TLC. (Box 6)
  - Mission, Santa Barbara Santa Barbara County, California, Established September 17th, 1804. View from Olive Orchard, looking North., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1222; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BE: surface loss, 12-1/4" from LE. BRC missing. RE: crease from BRC to 2" mark. RE: line near RE at 9-1/4". RE: small surface loss, 12-1/4". TE: small surface loss. TRC loss. TE: small surface loss, 3/4" from TLC. (Box 6)
  - Mission, Santa Barbara Santa Barbara County, California, Established September 17th, 1804. View Looking West, [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1223; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. Fabric tape residue LE. All edges cockled. Loss TRC & BRC. BE: 1/2" tear, 9-3/8" from RE. LE: small tear, 10-1/2" from BE. (Box 6)
  - Mission San Luis Rey de Francia, Estab. June 13, 1798. From Watkins' Yosemite Art Gallery, Portrait and Landscape, 26 Montgomery Street, and Woodward's Gardens, S.F., Watkins Series no. 4609; Matt Dimensions: 16.5 × 10.5 Cabinet card (Box 1, Folder 1/5)
  - Mission, Santa Ynez Santa Barbara County, California, Established September 17th, 1804., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1224; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BE: dent 4" from LE. BE: 1-1/2" tear 10- 1/2" from LE. Loss BLC, LRC, TRC. Surface loss bottom of RE. Surface loss left end TE. Spot on TC. (Box 6)
  - Mission, Santa Ynez Santa Barbara County, California, Established September 17th, 1804., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1225; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. Small loss all corners. Bottom edge worn. RE: small tear 8-3/4" from bottom edge. RE: 1/4" tear 9-1/4" from BE. (Box 7)
  - Mission, San Luis Obispo San Luis Obispo County, California, Established Sept. 1st, 1772., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1226; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BE & TE discolored TLC & BRC small loss. (Box 7)
  - Mission, San Luis Obispo San Luis Obispo County, California, Established Sept. 1st, 1772. General View, looking north., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1227; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. BRC & TLC loss. BE surface loss 8-3/4" from RE. TRC small surface loss. TE: small tear 13" from RE. TE: small loss 2" from LE. (Box 7)
  - Mission, San Miguel San Luis Obispo County, California, Established July 25th, 1797., [ca. 1882]; Watkins Series no. 1228; Plate Dimensions: 38 × 54 Matt Dimensions: 50 × 65 Mammoth print No visible damage. All edges cockled. Fabric tape residue along LE. Small loss all 4 corners. BE: 1/2" tear, 12" from LE. RE: small tear, 2-1/8" from BE. (Box 7)